现在我们知道了两个用户可以通过共享一个密钥
来保护通信数据
Now that we know how two users can protect
data using a shared secret key, the next
接下来的问题是，开始时，这两个用户如何产生
这么一个共享密钥？
question is how did these two users
generate a shared secret key to begin
这个问题将把我们带入公钥密码的世界
with? This question will take us into the
world of public key cryptography. In this
本章中，我们将看一些玩具似的密钥交换协议
module, we will look at a few toy key
exchange protocols as a way to introduce
作为引入公钥密码的主要思想的一种方法。
我们将回头讨论密钥交换
the main ideas of public key cryptography.
We're gonna come back and talk about key
并设计安全的密钥交换协议，这些将在我们构建
一些公钥工具之后讲
exchange and design secure key exchange
protocols after we build a few more public
试想一下，世界上有N位用户
key tools. So imagine for a second that
there a N users in the world. And the
问题是，这些用户如何管理这些密钥？
question is, how do these users manage
these secret keys that they're gonna use
他们要使用这些密钥来互相通信的。比如说，
to communicate with one another? So, for
example, let's assume N equals four and
我们假设N等于4，世界上有4位用户。一种方案是
there are four users in the world. One
option is that basically every pair of
每一对用户都共享一对密钥。这样的话，比如说
users will share a shared secret key. And
so, for example, U1 and U3 will share a
U1和U3共享一个密钥，我记之为K13。U1和U2共享一个密钥
shared, a shared secret key. I'll call it
K13. U1 and U2 will share a, a shared
我们记之为K12，等等。。K24、K34，等等
secret key. We'll call it K12 so on and so
forth. K24 K34 and so on and so forth. K14
K14和最后的K23。这种方法的问题是
and finally K23. The problem with this
approach is that now there are many, many
用户需要管理太多的共享密钥了。特别地
shared keys that users have to manage. And
in particular, every user has to store on
每个用户必须存储N个密钥，如果他要和
这个世界上N个其他用户对话
the order of N keys if he's gonna talk to
N other parties in this world. So the
那么问题是，我们能否做得比每个用户存储N个密钥更好？
question is can we do any better than
storing N keys per user? And the answer is
有一种方法叫做在线可信任第三方
yes. And one way to do that is what's
called an online trusted third party. I'll
我将使用TTP来表示可信任第三方
use TTP to denote that trusted third
party. So the way we are going to use the
我们将以这样的方式使用可信任第三方：
每个用户与可信任第三方共享一个单独的密钥
trusted third party is every user will now
share a single key with this trusted third
那么用户1会共享一个密钥，用户2会共享一个密钥
party. So user one will share a secret
key, user two will share a secret key. And
这是我们的朋友Alice和Bob，记他们的密钥为k_A和k_B
here are our friends Alice and Bob, let's
call their secret keys k sub A and k sub B.
现在这个设计的好处是每个用户只需
Okay, so now the nice thing about
this design is that now every user only
记住一个密钥。现在问题是
has to remember one secret key. The
question is now, what happens when Alice
当Alice想和Bob通信时，会发生什么？
双方必须参加某个特定的协议
wants to talk to Bob? Somehow the two of
them have to engage in a certain protocol,
在协议的最后，他们会共享一个密钥K_AB
such that at the end of this protocol they
will have a shared secret key K_AB that the
而攻击者不能知道K_AB。那么问题是
attacker wouldn't be able to know. And so
the question is how do Alice and Bob
Alice和Bob如何生成这一共享密钥K_AB呢？
我们来看一个这样一个玩具似的协议
generate this shared secret key KAB. So
let's look at an example toy protocol for
这里我们有朋友Alice和Bob。通常
doing that. So here we have our friends
Alice and Bob. As usual Bob has his key
Bob有他的密钥K_B，K_B是与可信任第三方共享的。
Alice有她的密钥K_A
KB, which is shared with a trusted third
party. Alice has her secret key KA,
K_A也是与可信任第三方共享的。所以
which is also shared with a trusted third
party. So here the trusted third party
可信任第三方同时知道K_A和K_B。问题是，
他们如何生成一个双方都同意的共享密钥
has both KA and KB. And the question is,
how do they generate a shared key that
但攻击者不知道这个共享密钥？
they both agree on, but the attacker would
have no idea what this shared key is? So
这里我们要看一个玩具协议。特别地
here we're only gonna look at a toy
protocol. In particular, this protocol is
这个协议对窃听是安全的
only gonna to be secure against
eavesdropping. It's not gonna be secure
它对篡改或主动攻击不安全。我说过待会我们会回来
against more tampering or active attacks.
As I said, we're gonna come back and
在稍后的课程里设计安全的密钥交换协议
design secure key exchange protocols later
on in the course. But for now, just to
但现在，只是为了引入密钥交换的想法，
我们看这个最简单的机制
introduce this idea of key exchange, let's
look at the simplest, simplest mechanism
它对窃听是安全的。换句话说
that's only secure against eavesdropping.
So in other words, adversary that listens
攻击者监听会话也不知道共享密钥K_AB
to the conversation won't know what
the shared key KAB is gonna be. And so the
这个协议如下工作。Alice开始时会发送一条信息
protocol works as follows. Alice is going
to start by sending a message to the
给可信任第三方，说：我想要一个密钥，用于跟Bob通信
trusted third party saying, hey I want a
secret key that's going to be shared with
可信任第三方会选择
Bob. What the trusted third party will do
is it will actually go ahead and choose a
一个随机密钥K_AB。那么可信任第三方
random secret key, KAB. So the trusted
third party is the one who's gonna
生成了他们的共享密钥。它会如下处理这个密钥
generate their shared secret key. And what
it will do with this key is the following.
它会回复一条信息给Alice。这条信息包含两部分
It's gonna send one message back to
Alice. But this message consists of, of
信息的第一部分是使用Alice的密钥K_A加密的信息
two parts. The first part of the message
is an encryption using Alice's secret key,
这个密钥在Alice和Bob之间使用
using the key KA, of the message. This key
is supposed to be used between parties
她把密钥K_AB包含在这条信息里
Alice and Bob, and she includes the secret
key KAB inside the message. Okay? So just
为了清楚点，这里的被加密的信息
to be clear, what's happening here is that
the message that gets encrypted is the key
是密钥K_AB加上"这个密钥是Alice和Bob的共享密钥"这一事实
KAB plus the fact that this key is
supposed to be a shared key between Alice
这整条信息使用了Alice的密钥加密
and Bob. Okay. And this whole message is
encrypted using Alice's secret key. The
TTP发给Alice的信息的另一部分叫做票据
other part of the message that the TTP
sends to Alice is what's called a ticket.
这个票据是为Bob加密的信息
And this ticket is basically a message
that's encrypted for Bob. So in other
换句话说，这个票据是用密钥K_B加密的
words, the ticket is gonna be an
encryption under the key KB of, again, the
加密的内容依然是"这个密钥将在Alice和Bob之间使用"
fact that this key is supposed to be used
between Alice and Bob. And she
然后TTP把这个事实附在密钥K_AB后面
concatenates to that the, the secret key,
KAB. Okay, so again, the message that's
票据中加密的信息是一个事实，这个事实说
这个密钥在Alice和Bob之间使用
encrypted inside of the ticket is the fact
that this key is to be used by Alice and
密钥K_AB也包含在票据里
Bob. And, the secret key, KAB, is included
in the ticket as well. Okay, So these two
这两条信息，让我圈出它们。这两条信息
messages, Here, let me circle them. These
two messages are sent from the trusted
由可信任第三方发送给Alice。现在我应该提一下
third party to Alice. Now I should mention
that the encryption system E that is
这里使用的加密系统E是一个CPA安全密码，
我们待会会看到为什么需要这一要求
actually being used here is a CPA secure
cipher and we'll see why that's needed in
那么，Alice与可信任第三方的回合结束了
just a minute. So, this is the end of the
conversation between Alice and this
如我们所说，在这个会话的最后
trusted third party. Basically as we
said at the end of this conversation,
Alice收到一条为她加密的信息
Alice receives one message that's
encrypted for her and another message
另一条信息叫做票据，是为Bob加密的。
稍后当Alice想和Bob安全通信时
called a ticket that's encrypted for Bob.
Now at a later time when Alice wants to
Alice当然会解密给她的
communicate securely with Bob what she
will do, is of course, she will decrypt
那部分信息。换句话说，她会解密用密钥K_A
her part of the message. In other words
she will decrypt the cipher text that was
加密的密文，现在Alice有了密钥K_AB。然后给Bob
encrypted using the key KA and now she has
the key KAB. And then to Bob, she's going
她把票据给Bob。Bob将收到这个票据
to send over this ticket. Bob is going
to receive the ticket and he is going to
他将使用他自己的密钥K_B来解密票据，然后他会
use his own secret key KB to decrypt it and
then he himself will also recover the
还原出密钥K_AB。那么现在他们有了共享密钥K_AB
secret key KAB. So now they have the
shared secret key KAB that they can use
他们可以使用K_AB来安全通信了。第一个问题是
to communicate securely with one another.
And the first question to ask is, Why is
为什么这个协议是安全的？即使我们只考虑窃听攻击者
this protocol secure? Even if we only
consider eavesdropping adversaries. So,
我们想一会。当我们只关心
let's think about that for a minute. So,
at the moment all we care about is just
对窃听的安全时，我们想想
security against an eavesdropper, So let's
think. What does an eavesdropper see in
窃听者在这个协议中看到两个密文
this protocol. Well basically he sees
these two cipher texts. Right, he sees the
他看到为Alice加密的密文。他看到了给Bob的票据
cipher text that's encrypted for Alice.
And then he sees the ticket that's
事实上他可以看到很多这样的信息
encrypted for Bob. And in fact he might
see many instances of these messages, in
特别是如果Alice和Bob连续地以这样的方式交换密钥
particular if Alice and Bob continuously
exchange keys in this way he's gonna see
他会看到很多这类信息，我们的目标是，
他没有任何关于交换密钥K_AB的信息
many messages of this type and our goal is
to say that he has no information about
那么这点可由密码E,D的CPA安全性直接得到
the exchanged key KAB. So this follows
directly from the CPA security of the
因为窃听者不能真正区分
cipher E D because the eavesdropper can't
really distinguish between encryptions of
密钥K_AB的加密和某个随机字符串的加密
the secret key KAB from encryption of just
random junk. That's the definition of CPA
这是CPA安全的定义，因此攻击者不能区分密钥K_AB
security and as a result, he can't
distinguish the key KAB from, you know,
与某个随机字符串，意味着攻击者不知道K_AB
random junk which means that he learns
nothing about KAB. This is kind of a very
这是很高层次的观点了，解释了为什么对窃听是安全的
high level argument for why this is
eavesdropping security but it's enough for
达到我们这里的目标了。至少在这个协议里
our purposes here. So the bottom line is
that in this protocol the eavesdropper
窃听者实际上没有任何关于K_AB的信息
would actually have no information about
what KAB is. And therefore it's okay to
因此可以使用K_AB作为Alice和Bob之间交换信息的密钥
use KAB as secret key to exchange messages
between Alice and Bob. Now let's think
我们想一想TTP。首先，大家注意到
about the TTP for a minute. So first of
all, you notice that the TTP is needed for
对于每个密钥交换，TTP是需要的。Alice和Bob不能
every single key exchange. So basically
Alice and Bob simply cannot do key change
交换密钥，除非TTP在线并且能够帮助他们
unless the TTP is online and available to
help them do that. And the other property
这个协议的另一个性质是，事实上，TTP知道所有的会话密钥
of this protocol is in fact, the TTP knows
all the session keys. So if somehow the
如果TTP沦陷了，可能TTP被破解了，那么攻击者可以
TTP is corrupt, or maybe it's broken into,
then an attacker can very easily steal all
轻松获得所有系统中用户之间已经交换过的密钥
the secret keys that have been exchanged
between every user of this system. This is
这就是问什么TTP被叫做可信任第三方
why this TTP is called the Trusted Third
Party because, essentially, it knows all
它知道系统中所有生成的回合密钥
the session keys that have been generated
in the system. Nevertheless the beauty of
不过这个机制漂亮的一点是，它只使用对称密钥密码学
this mechanism is that it only uses
symmetric key cryptography, nothing beyond
没有用任何我们还没见过的技术，因此它是快速有效的
what we've already seen and as a result it is
very fast and efficient. The only issue is
唯一的问题是，必须使用这个在线可信任第三方，
而且有一点还不是很清楚
that you have to use this online trusted
party and it's not immediately clear if for
例如，如果我们想在万维网中使用这个
example we wanted to use this in the
world wide web who would function as this
而万维网提供这个可信任第三方的功能。但是
在公司设定里，这个实际上有道理
online trusted third party. However, in a
corporate setting this might actually make
如果你有一个公司和一个可信任的点
sense if you have a single company with a
single point of trust it might make sense
是可以设计一个可信任第三方的机器的
to actually designate a machine as a
trusted third party. And in fact a
事实上，像这样的机制还不完全是我描述的那样
mechanism like this not quite as the way I
described it, but a mechanism like this is
但一个像这样的机制是Kerberos系统的基础。
那么这是我们的第一个密钥交换协议的例子
the basis of the Kerberos system. So
this is our first example of a key
允许Alice和Bob建立共享密钥
exchange protocol that allowed Alice and
Bob to set up shared keys, however I
但我很想指出，这只是一个玩具协议，非常简单
really want to point out that this is just
a toy protocol. Very, very simple and is
而且只对窃听攻击安全
only secure against eavesdropping
attack. It's actually completely insecure
对主动攻击是完全不安全的。这是一个很简单的例子
against an active attacker. And here's a
very simple example of how an active
展示了一个主动攻击者是如何破坏这个协议的，
那么我们来看看重放攻击
attacker might destroy this protocol, and
so let's just look at replay attacks. So
设想攻击者记下了Alice和某个在线商家的会话
here imagine the attacker records the
conversation between Alice and some online
我们叫做商家Bob。例如，设想一下
merchant. Let's call him Merchant Bob. So
for example, imagine Alice orders a book
Alice从商家Bob那里订购了一本书，交易完成
from the merchant Bob and the transaction
completes and Bob accepts payment for this
Bob接收了这本书的付款，然后发给Alice一份这本书的拷贝
book. And actually sends Alice a copy
of this book. What an attacker can do now
攻击者现在完全可以记下这段会话
is, he can complete, completely record the
conversation and simply replay the
稍后向商家Bob重放这段会话，Bob就会认为
conversation to merchant Bob at a later
time. Bob will think that Alice just
Alice刚刚重新订购了这本书的另一份拷贝，
Bob就会再收一次Alice的钱
reordered another, another copy of the
book and he'll charge her again for it,
然后发给Alice这份拷贝
and send her this, this copy again. So
essentially by replaying a conversation
所以重放会话会对Alice造成巨大危害
you can cause quite a bit of harm to
Alice, and as a result this is a simple
因此这是一个简单例子，揭示了这个协议对
主动攻击是完全不安全的
example of why this protocol is completely
insecure against active attacks, and
在现实中永远不应该被使用的。如我所说，
未来几周我们将回来
should never be used in the real world. As
I said we're going to come back in a few weeks
讨论这个协议的安全版本，大家会看到
and talk about secure versions of this
protocol, and you'll see how to make this
如何让这个协议在现实中正确工作。不过大家看到
work, in the real world. Nevertheless, you
see that this, this very simple protocol
这个非常简单的协议已经提出了很有趣的问题
already raises a very interesting
question. And the question is, can we
这个问题是，我们能否设计出密钥交换协议
basically design key exchange protocols
whether they're secure against
对窃听和主动攻击都保持安全呢？问题是
eavesdropping or secure against active
attackers. The question is, can we design
我们能否设计安全的密钥交换协议，
但不需要一个在线的可信任第三方
key exchange protocols that are secure,
but work without an online trusted third
那么我们不想依赖于任何可信任第三方
party. So we don't wanna rely on any
online trusted party that's necessary to
来完成这个密钥交换协议。令人惊奇的答案是
complete the key exchange protocol. And so
the amazing answer is that in fact this is
事实上这是可能的。我们可以不需要可信任第三方
就能交换密钥。事实上
possible. We can do key exchange without a
trusted third party. And this is, in fact,
这是公钥密码学的起点。我将为大家展示三种思路
the starting point of public cryptography.
So I'm gonna show you three ideas for
让这点可行，我们将在后面几章讨论它们的更多细节
making this happen and we're gonna talk
about them in much more detail in the, in
第一个思路是由Ralph Merkle于1974年提出的
the coming modules. So the first idea is
actually due to Ralph Merkle back in 1974.
当时他还是本科生
This was, he was, when he was just an
undergraduate student. And already he came
他就已经想出这个非常漂亮的
不需要可信任第三方的密钥交换的想法
up with this really nice idea for key
exchange without an online trusted third
我们将看一个他的想法的例子
party. So that's one example that
we're gonna look at. Another example is
另一个例子是Diffie与Hellman于1976年提出
due to Diffie and Hellman. Back in 1976
they both actually, working here at
当时他们都在斯坦福大学，他们提出的这个想法
开创了现代密码学的新世界
Stanford University, came up with this idea
that launched the world of modern key
第三个想法是由麻省理工的Rivest，Shamir和Adleman提出
cryptography. And the third idea is due to
Rivest, Shamir and Adleman working at MIT and
我们将看这些想法的细节
we're going to look in detail exactly how
each of these ideas work. But I do want to
但我很想提到，公共密钥管理的研究并未止步于1970年代
mention that the work on public key
management hasn't stopped in the late
事实上这些年来有很多想法被提出
seventies. In fact there have been many
ideas over the years and here I'll just
我只提过去10年间的两个想法。
一个叫做基于身份的加密(IBE)
mention two from the last decade. One is
call identity based encryption, which is
这是另一种管理公钥的方法。另一种想法叫做泛函加密
another way for managing public keys. And
another is called functional encryption,
这是一种给密钥的方法，只部分解密一个给定的密文
which is a way of giving secret keys that
only partially decrypt a given cipher text.
我们将在这两周讨论公钥密码学的核心内容
And so we're gonna talk about the core of
public key crypto in this and the next week
我们在本课程稍后讨论更多高级想法的细节
and we'll talk about these more advanced
ideas later on in the course.